<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Traffic Assignment | Debojjal Bagchi | Personal website</title><link>https://debojjalb.github.io/tags/traffic-assignment/</link><atom:link href="https://debojjalb.github.io/tags/traffic-assignment/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Traffic Assignment</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://debojjalb.github.io/media/icon_hu_645fa481986063ef.png</url><title>Traffic Assignment</title><link>https://debojjalb.github.io/tags/traffic-assignment/</link></image><item><title>Error bounds for stochastic user equilibrium traffic assignment</title><link>https://debojjalb.github.io/publication/error-bounds/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://debojjalb.github.io/publication/error-bounds/</guid><description>&lt;div class="flex px-4 py-3 mb-6 rounded-md bg-primary-100 dark:bg-primary-900">
&lt;span class="pr-3 pt-1 text-primary-600 dark:text-primary-300">
&lt;svg height="24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 24 24">&lt;path fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round" stroke-width="1.5" d="m11.25 11.25l.041-.02a.75.75 0 0 1 1.063.852l-.708 2.836a.75.75 0 0 0 1.063.853l.041-.021M21 12a9 9 0 1 1-18 0a9 9 0 0 1 18 0m-9-3.75h.008v.008H12z"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/span>
&lt;span class="dark:text-neutral-300">The codebase and conference extended abstract is available on the buttons above article.&lt;/span>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>In stochastic user equilibrium traffic assignment, we derive bounds on the distance between a given feasible solution and the equilibrium solution. The intent is to provide guidance on termination criteria to reduce runtimes, which is important because the traffic assignment problem is often a subproblem of a more complex bilevel optimization. These mathematical bounds complement existing rules of thumb drawn empirically from numerical case studies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Our approach is based on Taylor&amp;rsquo;s theorem, applied to the fixed-point formulation of the stochastic user equilibrium assignment, and provides upper bounds on differences in both aggregate metrics (average link travel cost, total system travel time) and disaggregate metrics (link flows, path flows). We demonstrate that the proposed path flow, link flow, and travel cost bounds are tight and cannot be further improved without additional restrictions on the network topology or problem instance.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Results on city-level networks indicate that the bounds on path flows are reasonably tight, with the absolute difference between the derived bound and actual value often in the order of $10^{-1}$. We study the tradeoff between the distance from equilibrium—where the bound becomes applicable—and its tightness. Detailed results guide the choice of a parameter that yields the tightest possible bound for a given distance from equilibrium. Empirical evidence shows that the bound on the distance between any feasible path flow and the equilibrium flow exhibits a near-linear rate of convergence close to equilibrium. This convergence rate is found to be close to $0.9$, consistent across all tested networks.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Finally, we demonstrate the practical utility of the derived bounds in a simple network design problem to find optimal link closures. By enumerating the complete feasible set, we show a 36% improvement in computation time on the Sioux Falls network when using the derived bounds, compared to not using them.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="flex px-4 py-3 mb-6 rounded-md bg-primary-100 dark:bg-primary-900">
&lt;span class="pr-3 pt-1 text-primary-600 dark:text-primary-300">
&lt;svg height="24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 24 24">&lt;path fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round" stroke-width="1.5" d="m11.25 11.25l.041-.02a.75.75 0 0 1 1.063.852l-.708 2.836a.75.75 0 0 0 1.063.853l.041-.021M21 12a9 9 0 1 1-18 0a9 9 0 0 1 18 0m-9-3.75h.008v.008H12z"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/span>
&lt;span class="dark:text-neutral-300">Click the &lt;em>Cite&lt;/em> button above to cite this article.&lt;/span>
&lt;/div></description></item></channel></rss>